<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Roman Catholick soldier's letter to Dr. Tho. Tenison</title>
            <author>Ward, Thomas, 1652-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W835</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12648447</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12648447</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65226</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 905:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Roman Catholick soldier's letter to Dr. Tho. Tenison</title>
                  <author>Ward, Thomas, 1652-1708.</author>
                  <author>Tenison, Thomas, 1636-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Broadside.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Ward. cf. NUC.</note>
                  <note>Signed: T. Ward.</note>
                  <note>Imprint taken from NUC.</note>
                  <note>A response to Tenison's response to Ward's Defence of the Speculum.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Broadsides</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65226:1"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Roman Catholick Souldiers</hi> LETTER TO Dr. Tho. Teniſon.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Doctor,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU and your <hi>A. B.</hi> has publiſh'd a <hi>Reply</hi> to my <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Speculum,</hi> before I either Printed or Publiſhed any ſuch thing. This is not to ſtay till all the Muſter-Roll be call'd over before you anſwer to your Name, as you ſay Mr. <hi>P.</hi> would have had you to have done; but 'tis every whit as abſurd, for 'tis to cry <hi>I am here, I am here,</hi> before ever you be call'd. This is a ſtrange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of way of proceeding.</p>
            <p>You write an Epiſtle to your <hi>A. B.</hi> in which you tell him and the World, that I was a <hi>Cambridge</hi> Scholar, and has chang'd my Black Coat for a Red one; I am ſorry you have gotten no better Information from your Enquiries after me at my Lodging, there having been no leſs than Two Men at one time, and Four at another (whether ſent by you or no, I will not ſay) making <hi>Enquiries</hi> of me at my Quarters, what I was? whether I had been an <hi>Oxford</hi> Scholar or no? was I no more than a Souldier? what I did? what I writ? with ſuch like <hi>Queries,</hi> to which the good people of the Houſe could give them little or no Anſwer, (as they told me) other than this, that they told ſome of them I was writing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning your Reverence, but they knew not what. Indeed Dr. your Oracles has deceiv'd you, and you have abus'd me by writing ſuch palpable and falſe untruths of me. For ſo far off was my thoughts from ever being either a <hi>Cambridge</hi> Scholar, or wearing a Clergy-Mans Black Coat, that on the contrary, I was a <hi>Catholick</hi> before I was 19 years of Age, and (God Almighty be prais'd) have remain'd a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> ever ſince, which is now other 19 years; which if I had but time to write into <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> I could prove by hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65226:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Witneſſes; nor had my Father (being a <hi>Calvinſt</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian</hi>) ever the leaſt thought of ſending me to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> or any other <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Univerſity, but rather of putting me to an Attorney, or ſome ſuch like Employ, till I loſt his kindneſs by Embracing the Holy <hi>Catholick Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that you have miſt the mark exceedingly, by ſaying I was, or ever was intended for a <hi>Cambridge</hi> Scholar, or had a Clergy-Mans Black Coat to change for a Military Red one. This ſtory's juſt like your Jeſuits with yellow Peruick and little Bands, and the ſholes of Men that throng'd in with Mr. P. in the Conference, when he has prov'd <hi>by</hi> 22 or 23 Witneſſes, that he brought but one Man with him, and he was neither a Prieſt, nor came to Diſpute, but only to be a Witneſs of what paſſed. If you go on at this rate, 'twil be time for Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> to look about him, you'l darken his luſture quite. What can we expect from the reſt of your Pamphlet, (call'd your <hi>Conſiderations on the Speculum Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticum</hi>) when you entertain us with ſuch a Whiskerat the firſt; may we not gueſs what you have in your ſhop by what you hang out of the window? If you would have had us given credit to your following Conſideration, <hi>(as you term it)</hi> you ſhould not have begun with ſo groſs an untruth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what ever we find in your Treatiſe deliver'd from your own word, without ſufficient proof, you muſt excuſe us if we do not, nor cannot believe it.</p>
            <p>I had not time to take much notice of your Pamphlet, only this I obſerv'd that you have found out a ready way to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the Fathers: That is, either by calling their Works Spurius and ſuppoſſititious, making a great ſhew with the Names of your Authors, but taking care not to Cite the places where any of their words may be found: Or elſe reckoning the Fathers words no other than <hi>Hiſtorical Apoſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes. p.</hi> 69. <hi>Complements to the Pope, meer Complements. p.</hi> 52. <hi>meer Rhetorical Flights, Rhetorical Apostrophes, p.</hi> 62. preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to tell us, that <hi>Orators</hi> (meaning the <hi>Holy Fathers,</hi> for of them you are ſpeaking) <hi>ſeldom contains themſelves within the ſevere bounds of Truths. p.</hi> 63. [well ſaid Doctor!] nor have you taken the leaſt notice of the Teſtimonies of Holy Scripture, why did you not Confute them alſo?</p>
            <p>What I have to ſay more Dr. is to adviſe you to wrap up your next of this nature a little cloſer than you have done this, or thoſe againſt Mr. <hi>P.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>From him who is always ready to ſerve you, <hi>T. Ward.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
